since Elon Musk took over Twitter many
people that don't like him or don't
agree with his policies have been
migrating to Mastodon a rival social
media platform in a matter of weeks
Marston went from 300 000 daily active
users to 2.5 million on the surface you
could say that Mastodon is a Twitter
Club because it sort of works the way
Twitter does you have a profile you can
follow some people you see their posts
you can retweet their posts like it or
reply to it but at its core Mastodon is
very different from Twitter first of all
there is no algorithm pushing ads or
Trends or suggested posts your timeline
is chronological from newest to oldest
and that's it second Mastodon is open
source we can go to the GitHub page and
see how the sausage is made the back end
is built with Ruby on Rails node.js is
used for streaming and react.js and
redox for the front end but the most
important thing of all and what makes
Mastodon so different from Twitter what
makes Mastodon awesome and what makes
people not want to use Mastodon is the
fact that Macedon is decentralized
thanks to the fact that Macedon is open
source anyone can download the code from
GitHub and run their own version of
Mastodon on their own server making what
is called an instance if you want to
join Mastodon you can run your own
instance which many people don't do or
you can find an already existing server
usually run by a volunteer that let you
join in this aspect Mastodon is less
than Twitter and more like email there
are many email providers and you get to
choose which one you use same with
muscle at the time of recording this
video there are more than 9 000 servers
running the Mastodon code but just
because they run the same software does
not mean that the servers are all the
same the person running the Mastodon
server has all the control and gets to
make all the rules some servers allow
you to join freely and some make you
apply for a membership some servers are
only for gamers or book readers with
strong moderation rules that would
delete or ban any off-topic posts there
are servers only for people of specific
political views Eco Chambers or people
that live in cities like Berlin or New
York or servers only for adults servers
where there is no moderation and
everything goes and even servers with
hateful content as well with email if I
use Gmail and you use protonmail we can
still talk to each other because both of
those email providers speak the email
protocol Mastodon is the same even if
you are on the Lord of the Rings server
and I am on the Thailand server we can
still follow each other and see each
other's posts that is because Mastodon
servers speak a protocol called activity
pop but this is not mandatory if you
want to you can make a completely
private Mastodon instance that does not
talk to anyone else these decentralized
architecture is the reason why a
mastodon username looks a lot more like
an email address first comes your
username and then the server where you
have your account on Mastered on that
social is one of the most popular
servers so if I was on that server my
username would be at Nico
macedon.social for example because
Mastodon is decentralized it cannot be
bought or sold it will not go bankrupt
and no person has absolute control over
it but because it is decentralized that
means that it has other challenges the
volunteer that runs the instance the
admin has to pay for the servers
databases and storage space from their
own pocket or using the donations that
same admin can see all the data on the
server including direct messages the
admin can ban you from the server and
kick you out if they feel like it and
there is nothing you can do and because
there is no Central authority to verify
if a user is real or not it is
relatively easy to impersonate a user
across many different servers with fake
accounts many people moved out of
Twitter because they don't want to trust
a billionaire with their data but
nevertheless unless they run their own
server they're going to have to trust
someone anyways maybe it's not Elon
anymore but it's now a random dude in
Bucharest many people including Mastodon
users don't see Mastodon replacing
Twitter because masterton as you can see
is different and it doesn't want to be
Twitter anyways that's it for this video
I hope that you like this tiny
introduction to masterton and I hope
that now you understand what is it and
how it is different from Twitter I now
would love to know what you think about
Mastodon did you know it was
decentralized do you think that it will
replace Twitter are you already using
Mastodon let me know in the comments and
if you like this kind of content please
consider leaving a like And subscribe
and don't forget that if you want to
learn things like JavaScript python
react react native gold dark Slaughter
among many others for absolutely free
all you have to do is click the link
below to join any of our many free
courses that you can take right now for
free click on the link below and I will
see you there
see you on the next one bye
[Music]